<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/manila/doc/source/install/common/share-node-share-server-modes.rst">
    <paragraph>The share node can support two modes, with and without the handling of
        share servers. The mode depends on driver support.</paragraph>
    <section ids="option-1" names="option\ 1">
        <title>Option 1</title>
        <paragraph>Deploying the service without driver support for share server management.
            In this mode, the service does not do anything related to networking. The
            operator must ensure network connectivity between instances and the NAS
            protocol based server.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>This tutorial demonstrates setting up the LVM driver which creates LVM volumes
            on the share node and exports them with the help of an NFS server that is
            installed locally on the share node. It therefore requires LVM and NFS packages
            as well as an additional disk for the <literal>manila-share</literal> LVM volume group.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>This driver mode may be referred to as <literal>driver_handles_share_servers = False</literal>
            mode, or simply <literal>DHSS=False</literal> mode.</paragraph>
    </section>
    <section ids="option-2" names="option\ 2">
        <title>Option 2</title>
        <paragraph>Deploying the service with driver support for share server management. In
            this mode, the service runs with a back end driver that creates and manages
            share servers. This tutorial demonstrates setting up the <literal>Generic</literal> driver.
            This driver requires Compute service (nova), Image service (glance) and
            Networking service (neutron) for creating and managing share servers; and
            Block storage service (cinder) for creating shares.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The information used for creating share servers is configured with the help of
            share networks.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>This driver mode may be referred to as <literal>driver_handles_share_servers = True</literal>
            mode, or simply <literal>DHSS=True</literal> mode.</paragraph>
        <warning>
            <paragraph>When running the generic driver in <literal>DHSS=True</literal> driver mode, the share
                service should be run on the same node as the networking service.
                However, such a service may not be able to run the LVM driver that runs
                in <literal>DHSS=False</literal> driver mode effectively, due to a bug in some
                distributions of Linux. For more information, see LVM Driver section in the
                <reference name="Configuration Reference Guide" refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/ocata/config-reference/shared-file-systems.html">Configuration Reference Guide</reference><target ids="configuration-reference-guide" names="configuration\ reference\ guide" refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/ocata/config-reference/shared-file-systems.html"></target>.</paragraph>
        </warning>
    </section>
</document>
