<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/nova/doc/source/user/architecture.rst">
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright 2010-2011 United States Government as represented by the
Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.
All Rights Reserved.

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain
a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.</comment>
    <section ids="nova-system-architecture" names="nova\ system\ architecture">
        <title>Nova System Architecture</title>
        <paragraph>Nova is comprised of multiple server processes, each performing different
            functions. The user-facing interface is a REST API, while internally Nova
            components communicate via an RPC message passing mechanism.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The API servers process REST requests, which typically involve database
            reads/writes, optionally sending RPC messages to other Nova services,
            and generating responses to the REST calls.
            RPC messaging is done via the <strong>oslo.messaging</strong> library,
            an abstraction on top of message queues.
            Most of the major nova components can be run on multiple servers, and have
            a <title_reference>manager</title_reference> that is listening for <title_reference>RPC</title_reference> messages.
            The one major exception is nova-compute, where a single process runs on the
            hypervisor it is managing (except when using the VMware or Ironic drivers).
            The manager also, optionally, has periodic tasks.
            For more details on our <title_reference>RPC</title_reference> system, please see: <reference internal="True" refuri="../reference/rpc"><inline classes="doc">AMQP and Nova</inline></reference></paragraph>
        <paragraph>Nova also uses a central database that is (logically) shared between all
            components. However, to aid upgrade, the DB is accessed through an object
            layer that ensures an upgraded control plane can still communicate with
            a nova-compute running the previous release.
            To make this possible nova-compute proxies DB requests over <title_reference>RPC</title_reference> to a
            central manager called <title_reference>nova-conductor</title_reference></paragraph>
        <paragraph>To horizontally expand Nova deployments, we have a deployment sharding
            concept called cells. For more information please see: <reference internal="True" refuri="cells"><inline classes="doc">Cells</inline></reference></paragraph>
        <section ids="components" names="components">
            <title>Components</title>
            <paragraph>Below you will find a helpful explanation of the key components
                of a typical (non-cells v1) Nova deployment.</paragraph>
            <image candidates="{'*': u'_static/images/architecture.svg'}" uri="_static/images/architecture.svg" width="100%"></image>
            <bullet_list bullet="*">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>DB: sql database for data storage.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>API: component that receives HTTP requests, converts commands and communicates with other components via the <strong>oslo.messaging</strong> queue or HTTP</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Scheduler: decides which host gets each instance</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Network: manages ip forwarding, bridges, and vlans</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Compute: manages communication with hypervisor and virtual machines.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Conductor: handles requests that need coordination(build/resize), acts as a
                        database proxy, or handles object conversions.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>While all services are designed to be horizontally scalable, you should have significantly more computes then anything else.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
