<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/cinder/doc/source/contributor/api.apache.rst">
    <comment xml:space="preserve">All Rights Reserved.

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain
a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.</comment>
    <section ids="running-cinder-api-under-apache" names="running\ cinder\ api\ under\ apache">
        <title>Running Cinder API under Apache</title>
        <section ids="files" names="files">
            <title>Files</title>
            <paragraph>Copy the file etc/cinder/api-httpd.conf to the appropriate location for your Apache server, most likely:</paragraph>
            <paragraph><literal>/etc/httpd/conf.d/cinder_wsgi.conf</literal></paragraph>
            <paragraph>Update this file to match your system configuration (for example, some distributions put httpd logs in the apache2 directory and some in the httpd directory).
                Create the directory /var/www/cgi-bin/cinder/. You can either hard or soft link the file cinder/wsgi/wsgi.py to be osapi_volume under the /var/www/cgi-bin/cinder/ directory. For a distribution appropriate place, it should probably be copied to:</paragraph>
            <paragraph><literal>/usr/share/openstack/cinder/httpd/cinder.py</literal></paragraph>
            <paragraph>Cinder’s primary configuration file (etc/cinder.conf) and the PasteDeploy configuration file (etc/cinder-paste.ini) must be readable to httpd in one of the default locations described in Configuring Cinder.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="access-control" names="access\ control">
            <title>Access Control</title>
            <paragraph>If you are running with Linux kernel security module enabled (for example SELinux or AppArmor), make sure that the configuration file has the appropriate context to access the linked file.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
