<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/manila/doc/source/configuration/shared-file-systems/overview.rst">
    <section ids="introduction-to-the-shared-file-systems-service" names="introduction\ to\ the\ shared\ file\ systems\ service">
        <title>Introduction to the Shared File Systems service</title>
        <paragraph>The Shared File Systems service provides shared file systems that
            Compute instances can consume.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The overall Shared File Systems service is implemented via the
            following specific services:</paragraph>
        <definition_list>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-api</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>A WSGI app that authenticates and routes requests
                        throughout the Shared File Systems service. It supports the OpenStack
                        APIs.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-data</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>A standalone service whose purpose is to receive requests, process data
                        operations with potentially long running time such as copying, share
                        migration or backup.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-scheduler</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>Schedules and routes requests to the appropriate
                        share service. The scheduler uses configurable filters and weighers
                        to route requests. The Filter Scheduler is the default and enables
                        filters on things like Capacity, Availability Zone, Share Types, and
                        Capabilities as well as custom filters.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-share</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>Manages back-end devices that provide shared file
                        systems. A manila-share service can run in one of two modes, with or
                        without handling of share servers. Share servers export file shares
                        via share networks. When share servers are not used, the networking
                        requirements are handled outside of Manila.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
        </definition_list>
        <paragraph>The Shared File Systems service contains the following components:</paragraph>
        <definition_list>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term><strong>Back-end storage devices</strong></term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>The Shared File Services service requires some form of back-end shared file
                        system provider that the service is built on. The reference implementation
                        uses the Block Storage service (Cinder) and a service VM to provide shares.
                        Additional drivers are used to access shared file systems from a variety of
                        vendor solutions.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term><strong>Users and tenants (projects)</strong></term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>The Shared File Systems service can be used by many different cloud
                        computing consumers or customers (tenants on a shared system), using
                        role-based access assignments.  Roles control the actions that a user is
                        allowed to perform. In the default configuration, most actions do not
                        require a particular role unless they are restricted to administrators, but
                        this can be configured by the system administrator in the appropriate
                        <literal>policy.json</literal> file that maintains the rules. A user’s access to manage
                        particular shares is limited by tenant. Guest access to mount and use shares
                        is secured by IP and/or user access rules. Quotas used to control resource
                        consumption across available hardware resources are per tenant.</paragraph>
                    <paragraph>For tenants, quota controls are available to limit:</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>The number of shares that can be created.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>The number of gigabytes that can be provisioned for shares.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>The number of share snapshots that can be created.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>The number of gigabytes that can be provisioned for share
                                snapshots.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>The number of share networks that can be created.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                    <paragraph>You can revise the default quota values with the Shared File Systems
                        CLI, so the limits placed by quotas are editable by admin users.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term><strong>Shares, snapshots, and share networks</strong></term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>The basic resources offered by the Shared File Systems service are shares,
                        snapshots and share networks:</paragraph>
                    <definition_list>
                        <definition_list_item>
                            <term><strong>Shares</strong></term>
                            <definition>
                                <paragraph>A share is a unit of storage with a protocol, a size, and an access list.
                                    Shares are the basic primitive provided by Manila. All shares exist on a
                                    backend. Some shares are associated with share networks and share
                                    servers. The main protocols supported are NFS and CIFS, but other
                                    protocols are supported as well.</paragraph>
                            </definition>
                        </definition_list_item>
                        <definition_list_item>
                            <term><strong>Snapshots</strong></term>
                            <definition>
                                <paragraph>A snapshot is a point in time copy of a share.  Snapshots can only be
                                    used to create new shares (containing the snapshotted data). Shares
                                    cannot be deleted until all associated snapshots are deleted.</paragraph>
                            </definition>
                        </definition_list_item>
                        <definition_list_item>
                            <term><strong>Share networks</strong></term>
                            <definition>
                                <paragraph>A share network is a tenant-defined object that informs Manila about the
                                    security and network configuration for a group of shares. Share networks
                                    are only relevant for backends that manage share servers. A share network
                                    contains a security service and network/subnet.</paragraph>
                            </definition>
                        </definition_list_item>
                    </definition_list>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
        </definition_list>
    </section>
</document>
