<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/neutron/doc/source/admin/config-ipam.rst">
    <target refid="config-ipam"></target>
    <section ids="ipam-configuration config-ipam" names="ipam\ configuration config-ipam">
        <title>IPAM configuration</title>
        <note>
            <paragraph>Experimental feature or incomplete documentation.</paragraph>
        </note>
        <paragraph>Starting with the Liberty release, OpenStack Networking includes a pluggable
            interface for the IP Address Management (IPAM) function. This interface creates
            a driver framework for the allocation and de-allocation of subnets and IP
            addresses, enabling the integration of alternate IPAM implementations or
            third-party IP Address Management systems.</paragraph>
        <section ids="the-basics" names="the\ basics">
            <title>The basics</title>
            <paragraph>In Liberty and Mitaka, the IPAM implementation within OpenStack Networking
                provided a pluggable and non-pluggable flavor. As of Newton, the non-pluggable
                flavor is no longer available. Instead, it is completely replaced with a
                reference driver implementation of the pluggable framework. All data will
                be automatically migrated during the upgrade process, unless you have
                previously configured a pluggable IPAM driver. In that case, no migration
                is necessary.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>To configure a driver other than the reference driver, specify it
                in the <literal>neutron.conf</literal> file. Do this after the migration is
                complete. There is no need to specify any value if you wish to use the
                reference driver.</paragraph>
            <literal_block highlight_args="{}" language="ini" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">ipam_driver = ipam-driver-name</literal_block>
            <paragraph>There is no need to specify any value if you wish to use the reference
                driver, though specifying <literal>internal</literal> will explicitly choose the reference
                driver. The documentation for any alternate drivers will include the value to
                use when specifying that driver.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="known-limitations" names="known\ limitations">
            <title>Known limitations</title>
            <bullet_list bullet="*">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>The driver interface is designed to allow separate drivers for each
                        subnet pool. However, the current implementation allows only a single
                        IPAM driver system-wide.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Third-party drivers must provide their own migration mechanisms to convert
                        existing OpenStack installations to their IPAM.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
