<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/neutron/doc/source/admin/intro-overlay-protocols.rst">
    <target refid="intro-overlay-protocols"></target>
    <section ids="overlay-tunnel-protocols intro-overlay-protocols" names="overlay\ (tunnel)\ protocols intro-overlay-protocols">
        <title>Overlay (tunnel) protocols</title>
        <paragraph>Tunneling is a mechanism that makes transfer of payloads feasible over an
            incompatible delivery network. It allows the network user to gain access to
            denied or insecure networks. Data encryption may be employed to transport the
            payload, ensuring that the encapsulated user network data appears as public
            even though it is private and can easily pass the conflicting network.</paragraph>
        <section ids="generic-routing-encapsulation-gre" names="generic\ routing\ encapsulation\ (gre)">
            <title>Generic routing encapsulation (GRE)</title>
            <paragraph>Generic routing encapsulation (GRE) is a protocol that runs over IP and is
                employed when delivery and payload protocols are compatible but payload
                addresses are incompatible. For instance, a payload might think it is running
                on a datalink layer but it is actually running over a transport layer using
                datagram protocol over IP. GRE creates a private point-to-point connection
                and works by encapsulating a payload. GRE is a foundation protocol for other
                tunnel protocols but the GRE tunnels provide only weak authentication.</paragraph>
            <target refid="vxlan"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="virtual-extensible-local-area-network-vxlan vxlan" names="virtual\ extensible\ local\ area\ network\ (vxlan) vxlan">
            <title>Virtual extensible local area network (VXLAN)</title>
            <paragraph>The purpose of VXLAN is to provide scalable network isolation. VXLAN is a
                Layer 2 overlay scheme on a Layer 3 network. It allows an overlay layer-2
                network to spread across multiple underlay layer-3 network domains. Each
                overlay is termed a VXLAN segment. Only VMs within the same VXLAN segment
                can communicate.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
