<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/swift/doc/source/overview_encryption.rst">
    <section ids="object-encryption" names="object\ encryption">
        <title>Object Encryption</title>
        <paragraph>Swift supports the optional encryption of object data at rest on storage nodes.
            The encryption of object data is intended to mitigate the risk of users’ data
            being read if an unauthorised party were to gain physical access to a disk.</paragraph>
        <note>
            <paragraph>Swift’s data-at-rest encryption accepts plaintext object data from the
                client, encrypts it in the cluster, and stores the encrypted data. This
                protects object data from inadvertently being exposed if a data drive
                leaves the Swift cluster. If a user wishes to ensure that the plaintext
                data is always encrypted while in transit and in storage, it is strongly
                recommended that the data be encrypted before sending it to the Swift
                cluster. Encrypting on the client side is the only way to ensure that the
                data is fully encrypted for its entire lifecycle.</paragraph>
        </note>
        <paragraph>Encryption of data at rest is implemented by middleware that may be included in
            the proxy server WSGI pipeline. The feature is internal to a Swift cluster and
            not exposed through the API. Clients are unaware that data is encrypted by this
            feature internally to the Swift service; internally encrypted data should never
            be returned to clients via the Swift API.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The following data are encrypted while at rest in Swift:</paragraph>
        <bullet_list bullet="*">
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Object content i.e. the content of an object PUT request’s body</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>The entity tag (ETag) of objects that have non-zero content</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>All custom user object metadata values i.e. metadata sent using
                    X-Object-Meta- prefixed headers with PUT or POST requests</paragraph>
            </list_item>
        </bullet_list>
        <paragraph>Any data or metadata not included in the list above are not encrypted,
            including:</paragraph>
        <bullet_list bullet="*">
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Account, container and object names</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Account and container custom user metadata values</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>All custom user metadata names</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Object Content-Type values</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Object size</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>System metadata</paragraph>
            </list_item>
        </bullet_list>
        <note>
            <paragraph>This feature is intended to provide <title_reference>confidentiality</title_reference> of data that is at
                rest i.e. to protect user data from being read by an attacker that gains
                access to disks on which object data is stored.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This feature is not intended to prevent undetectable <title_reference>modification</title_reference>
                of user data at rest.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>This feature is not intended to protect against an attacker that gains
                access to Swift’s internal network connections, or gains access to key
                material or is able to modify the Swift code running on Swift nodes.</paragraph>
        </note>
        <target refid="encryption-deployment"></target>
        <section ids="deployment-and-operation encryption-deployment" names="deployment\ and\ operation encryption_deployment">
            <title>Deployment and operation</title>
            <paragraph>Encryption is deployed by adding two middleware filters to the proxy
                server WSGI pipeline and including their respective filter configuration
                sections in the <title_reference>proxy-server.conf</title_reference> file. <reference internal="True" refid="container-sync-client-config"><inline classes="std std-ref">Additional steps</inline></reference> are required if the container sync feature is
                being used.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The <title_reference>keymaster</title_reference> and <title_reference>encryption</title_reference> middleware filters must be to the right of all
                other middleware in the pipeline apart from the final proxy-logging middleware,
                and in the order shown in this example:</paragraph>
            <literal_block xml:space="preserve">&lt;other middleware&gt; keymaster encryption proxy-logging proxy-server

[filter:keymaster]
use = egg:swift#keymaster
encryption_root_secret = your_secret

[filter:encryption]
use = egg:swift#encryption
# disable_encryption = False</literal_block>
            <paragraph>See the <title_reference>proxy-server.conf-sample</title_reference> file for further details on the middleware
                configuration options.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The keymaster config option <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> MUST be set to a value
                of at least 44 valid base-64 characters before the middleware is used and
                should be consistent across all proxy servers. The minimum length of 44 has
                been chosen because it is the length of a base-64 encoded 32 byte value.</paragraph>
            <note>
                <paragraph>The <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> option holds the master secret key used for
                    encryption.  The security of all encrypted data critically depends on this
                    key and it should therefore be set to a high-entropy value. For example, a
                    suitable <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> may be obtained by base-64 encoding a
                    32 byte (or longer) value generated by a cryptographically secure random
                    number generator.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> value is necessary to recover any encrypted
                    data from the storage system, and therefore, it must be guarded against
                    accidental loss. Its value (and consequently, the proxy-server.conf file)
                    should not be stored on any disk that is in any account, container or
                    object ring.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> value should not be changed once deployed.
                    Doing so would prevent Swift from properly decrypting data that was
                    encrypted using the former value, and would therefore result in the loss of
                    that data.</paragraph>
            </note>
            <paragraph>One method for generating a suitable value for <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> is to
                use the <literal>openssl</literal> command line tool:</paragraph>
            <literal_block xml:space="preserve">openssl rand -base64 32</literal_block>
            <paragraph>Once deployed, the encryption filter will by default encrypt object data and
                metadata when handling PUT and POST requests and decrypt object data and
                metadata when handling GET and HEAD requests. COPY requests are transformed
                into GET and PUT requests by the <reference internal="True" refuri="middleware#copy"><inline classes="std std-ref">Server Side Copy</inline></reference> middleware before reaching the
                encryption middleware and as a result object data and metadata is decrypted and
                re-encrypted when copied.</paragraph>
            <section ids="upgrade-considerations" names="upgrade\ considerations">
                <title>Upgrade Considerations</title>
                <paragraph>When upgrading an existing cluster to deploy encryption, the following sequence
                    of steps is recommended:</paragraph>
                <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Upgrade all object servers</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Upgrade all proxy servers</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Add keymaster and encryption middlewares to every proxy server’s middleware
                            pipeline with the encryption <literal>disable_encryption</literal> option set to <literal>True</literal>
                            and the keymaster <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> value set as described above.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>If required, follow the steps for <reference internal="True" refid="container-sync-client-config"><inline classes="std std-ref">Container sync configuration</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Finally, change the encryption <literal>disable_encryption</literal> option to <literal>False</literal></paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </enumerated_list>
                <paragraph>Objects that existed in the cluster prior to the keymaster and encryption
                    middlewares being deployed are still readable with GET and HEAD requests. The
                    content of those objects will not be encrypted unless they are written again by
                    a PUT or COPY request. Any user metadata of those objects will not be encrypted
                    unless it is written again by a PUT, POST or COPY request.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="disabling-encryption" names="disabling\ encryption">
                <title>Disabling Encryption</title>
                <paragraph>Once deployed, the keymaster and encryption middlewares should not be removed
                    from the pipeline. To do so will cause encrypted object data and/or metadata to
                    be returned in response to GET or HEAD requests for objects that were
                    previously encrypted.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Encryption of inbound object data may be disabled by setting the encryption
                    <literal>disable_encryption</literal> option to <literal>True</literal>, in which case existing encrypted
                    objects will remain encrypted but new data written with PUT, POST or COPY
                    requests will not be encrypted. The keymaster and encryption middlewares should
                    remain in the pipeline even when encryption of new objects is not required. The
                    encryption middleware is needed to handle GET requests for objects that may
                    have been previously encrypted. The keymaster is needed to provide keys for
                    those requests.</paragraph>
                <target refid="container-sync-client-config"></target>
            </section>
            <section ids="container-sync-configuration container-sync-client-config" names="container\ sync\ configuration container_sync_client_config">
                <title>Container sync configuration</title>
                <paragraph>If container sync is being used then the keymaster and encryption middlewares
                    must be added to the container sync internal client pipeline. The following
                    configuration steps are required:</paragraph>
                <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Create a custom internal client configuration file for container sync (if
                            one is not already in use) based on the sample file
                            <title_reference>internal-client.conf-sample</title_reference>. For example, copy
                            <title_reference>internal-client.conf-sample</title_reference> to <title_reference>/etc/swift/container-sync-client.conf</title_reference>.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Modify this file to include the middlewares in the pipeline in
                            the same way as described above for the proxy server.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Modify the container-sync section of all container server config files to
                            point to this internal client config file using the
                            <literal>internal_client_conf_path</literal> option. For example:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">internal_client_conf_path = /etc/swift/container-sync-client.conf</literal_block>
                    </list_item>
                </enumerated_list>
                <note>
                    <paragraph>The <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> value is necessary to recover any encrypted
                        data from the storage system, and therefore, it must be guarded against
                        accidental loss. Its value (and consequently, the custom internal client
                        configuration file) should not be stored on any disk that is in any
                        account, container or object ring.</paragraph>
                </note>
                <note>
                    <paragraph>These container sync configuration steps will be necessary for container
                        sync probe tests to pass if the encryption middlewares are included in the
                        proxy pipeline of a test cluster.</paragraph>
                </note>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section ids="implementation" names="implementation">
            <title>Implementation</title>
            <section ids="encryption-scheme" names="encryption\ scheme">
                <title>Encryption scheme</title>
                <paragraph>Plaintext data is encrypted to ciphertext using the AES cipher with 256-bit
                    keys implemented by the python <reference name="cryptography package" refuri="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/cryptography">cryptography package</reference><target ids="cryptography-package" names="cryptography\ package" refuri="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/cryptography"></target>. The cipher is used in counter
                    (CTR) mode so that any byte or range of bytes in the ciphertext may be
                    decrypted independently of any other bytes in the ciphertext. This enables very
                    simple handling of ranged GETs.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>In general an item of unencrypted data, <literal>plaintext</literal>, is transformed to an
                    item of encrypted data, <literal>ciphertext</literal>:</paragraph>
                <literal_block xml:space="preserve">ciphertext = E(plaintext, k, iv)</literal_block>
                <paragraph>where <literal>E</literal> is the encryption function, <literal>k</literal> is an encryption key and <literal>iv</literal>
                    is a unique initialization vector (IV) chosen for each encryption context. For
                    example, the object body is one encryption context with a randomly chosen IV.
                    The IV is stored as metadata of the encrypted item so that it is available for
                    decryption:</paragraph>
                <literal_block xml:space="preserve">plaintext = D(ciphertext, k, iv)</literal_block>
                <paragraph>where <literal>D</literal> is the decryption function.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The implementation of CTR mode follows <reference name="NIST SP800-38A" refuri="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-38a/sp800-38a.pdf">NIST SP800-38A</reference><target ids="nist-sp800-38a" names="nist\ sp800-38a" refuri="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-38a/sp800-38a.pdf"></target>, and the
                    full IV passed to the encryption or decryption function serves as the initial
                    counter block.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>In general any encrypted item has accompanying crypto-metadata that describes
                    the IV and the cipher algorithm used for the encryption:</paragraph>
                <literal_block xml:space="preserve">crypto_metadata = {"iv": &lt;16 byte value&gt;,
                   "cipher": "AES_CTR_256"}</literal_block>
                <paragraph>This crypto-metadata is stored either with the ciphertext (for user
                    metadata and etags) or as a separate header (for object bodies).</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="key-management" names="key\ management">
                <title>Key management</title>
                <paragraph>A keymaster middleware is responsible for providing the keys required for each
                    encryption and decryption operation. Two keys are required when handling object
                    requests: a <title_reference>container key</title_reference> that is uniquely associated with the container path
                    and an <title_reference>object key</title_reference> that is uniquely associated with the object path.  These
                    keys are made available to the encryption middleware via a callback function
                    that the keymaster installs in the WSGI request environ.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The current keymaster implementation derives container and object keys from the
                    <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> in a deterministic way by constructing a SHA256
                    HMAC using the <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal> as a key and the container or object
                    path as a message, for example:</paragraph>
                <literal_block xml:space="preserve">object_key = HMAC(encryption_root_secret, "/a/c/o")</literal_block>
                <paragraph>Other strategies for providing object and container keys may be employed by
                    future implementations of alternative keymaster middleware.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>During each object PUT, a random key is generated to encrypt the object body.
                    This random key is then encrypted using the object key provided by the
                    keymaster. This makes it safe to store the encrypted random key alongside the
                    encrypted object data and metadata.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>This process of <title_reference>key wrapping</title_reference> enables more efficient re-keying events when the
                    object key may need to be replaced and consequently any data encrypted using
                    that key must be re-encrypted. Key wrapping minimizes the amount of data
                    encrypted using those keys to just other randomly chosen keys which can be
                    re-wrapped efficiently without needing to re-encrypt the larger amounts of data
                    that were encrypted using the random keys.</paragraph>
                <note>
                    <paragraph>Re-keying is not currently implemented. Key wrapping is implemented
                        in anticipation of future re-keying operations.</paragraph>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section ids="encryption-middleware" names="encryption\ middleware">
                <title>Encryption middleware</title>
                <paragraph>The encryption middleware is composed of an <title_reference>encrypter</title_reference> component and a
                    <title_reference>decrypter</title_reference> component.</paragraph>
                <section ids="encrypter-operation" names="encrypter\ operation">
                    <title>Encrypter operation</title>
                    <section ids="custom-user-metadata" names="custom\ user\ metadata">
                        <title>Custom user metadata</title>
                        <paragraph>The encrypter encrypts each item of custom user metadata using the object key
                            provided by the keymaster and an IV that is randomly chosen for that metadata
                            item. The encrypted values are stored as <reference internal="True" refuri="development_middleware#transient-sysmeta"><inline classes="std std-ref">Object Transient-Sysmeta</inline></reference> with
                            associated crypto-metadata appended to the encrypted value. For example:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">X-Object-Meta-Private1: value1
X-Object-Meta-Private2: value2</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>are transformed to:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">X-Object-Transient-Sysmeta-Crypto-Meta-Private1:
  E(value1, object_key, header_iv_1); swift_meta={"iv": header_iv_1,
                                                  "cipher": "AES_CTR_256"}
X-Object-Transient-Sysmeta-Crypto-Meta-Private2:
  E(value2, object_key, header_iv_2); swift_meta={"iv": header_iv_2,
                                                  "cipher": "AES_CTR_256"}</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>The unencrypted custom user metadata headers are removed.</paragraph>
                    </section>
                    <section ids="object-body" names="object\ body">
                        <title>Object body</title>
                        <paragraph>Encryption of an object body is performed using a randomly chosen body key
                            and a randomly chosen IV:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">body_ciphertext = E(body_plaintext, body_key, body_iv)</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>The body_key is wrapped using the object key provided by the keymaster and a
                            randomly chosen IV:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">wrapped_body_key = E(body_key, object_key, body_key_iv)</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>The encrypter stores the associated crypto-metadata in a system metadata
                            header:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Body-Meta:
    {"iv": body_iv,
     "cipher": "AES_CTR_256",
     "body_key": {"key": wrapped_body_key,
                  "iv": body_key_iv}}</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>Note that in this case there is an extra item of crypto-metadata which stores
                            the wrapped body key and its IV.</paragraph>
                    </section>
                    <section ids="entity-tag" names="entity\ tag">
                        <title>Entity tag</title>
                        <paragraph>While encrypting the object body the encrypter also calculates the ETag (md5
                            digest) of the plaintext body. This value is encrypted using the object key
                            provided by the keymaster and a randomly chosen IV, and saved as an item of
                            system metadata, with associated crypto-metadata appended to the encrypted
                            value:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag:
  E(md5(plaintext), object_key, etag_iv); swift_meta={"iv": etag_iv,
                                                      "cipher": "AES_CTR_256"}</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>The encrypter also forces an encrypted version of the plaintext ETag to be sent
                            with container updates by adding an update override header to the PUT request.
                            The associated crypto-metadata is appended to the encrypted ETag value of this
                            update override header:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">X-Object-Sysmeta-Container-Update-Override-Etag:
    E(md5(plaintext), container_key, override_etag_iv);
    meta={"iv": override_etag_iv, "cipher": "AES_CTR_256"}</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>The container key is used for this encryption so that the decrypter is able
                            to decrypt the ETags in container listings when handling a container request,
                            since object keys may not be available in that context.</paragraph>
                        <paragraph>Since the plaintext ETag value is only known once the encrypter has completed
                            processing the entire object body, the <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag</literal> and
                            <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Container-Update-Override-Etag</literal> headers are sent after the
                            encrypted object body using the proxy server’s support for request footers.</paragraph>
                        <target refid="conditional-requests"></target>
                    </section>
                    <section ids="conditional-requests id1" names="conditional\ requests conditional_requests">
                        <title>Conditional Requests</title>
                        <paragraph>In general, an object server evaluates conditional requests with
                            <literal>If[-None]-Match</literal> headers by comparing values listed in an
                            <literal>If[-None]-Match</literal> header against the ETag that is stored in the object
                            metadata. This is not possible when the ETag stored in object metadata has been
                            encrypted. The encrypter therefore calculates an HMAC using the object key and
                            the ETag while handling object PUT requests, and stores this under the metadata
                            key <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag-Mac</literal>:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag-Mac: HMAC(object_key, md5(plaintext))</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>Like other ETag-related metadata, this is sent after the encrypted object body
                            using the proxy server’s support for request footers.</paragraph>
                        <paragraph>The encrypter similarly calculates an HMAC for each ETag value included in
                            <literal>If[-None]-Match</literal> headers of conditional GET or HEAD requests, and appends
                            these to the <literal>If[-None]-Match</literal> header. The encrypter also sets the
                            <literal>X-Backend-Etag-Is-At</literal> header to point to the previously stored
                            <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag-Mac</literal> metadata so that the object server
                            evaluates the conditional request by comparing the HMAC values included in the
                            <literal>If[-None]-Match</literal> with the value stored under
                            <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag-Mac</literal>. For example, given a conditional request
                            with header:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">If-Match: match_etag</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>the encrypter would transform the request headers to include:</paragraph>
                        <literal_block xml:space="preserve">If-Match: match_etag,HMAC(object_key, match_etag)
X-Backend-Etag-Is-At: X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag-Mac</literal_block>
                        <paragraph>This enables the object server to perform an encrypted comparison to check
                            whether the ETags match, without leaking the ETag itself or leaking information
                            about the object body.</paragraph>
                    </section>
                </section>
                <section ids="decrypter-operation" names="decrypter\ operation">
                    <title>Decrypter operation</title>
                    <paragraph>For each GET or HEAD request to an object, the decrypter inspects the response
                        for encrypted items (revealed by crypto-metadata headers), and if any are
                        discovered then it will:</paragraph>
                    <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Fetch the object and container keys from the keymaster via its callback</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Decrypt the <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Etag</literal> value</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Decrypt the <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Container-Update-Override-Etag</literal> value</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Decrypt metadata header values using the object key</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Decrypt the wrapped body key found in <literal>X-Object-Sysmeta-Crypto-Body-Meta</literal></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Decrypt the body using the body key</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </enumerated_list>
                    <paragraph>For each GET request to a container that would include ETags in its response
                        body, the decrypter will:</paragraph>
                    <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>GET the response body with the container listing</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Fetch the container key from the keymaster via its callback</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Decrypt any encrypted ETag entries in the container listing using the
                                container key</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </enumerated_list>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section ids="impact-on-other-swift-services-and-features" names="impact\ on\ other\ swift\ services\ and\ features">
                <title>Impact on other Swift services and features</title>
                <paragraph>Encryption has no impact on <reference internal="True" refuri="middleware#versioned-writes"><inline classes="std std-ref">Object Versioning</inline></reference> other than that any
                    previously unencrypted objects will be encrypted as they are copied to or from
                    the versions container. Keymaster and encryption middlewares should be placed
                    after <literal>versioned_writes</literal> in the proxy server pipeline, as described in
                    <reference internal="True" refid="encryption-deployment"><inline classes="std std-ref">Deployment and operation</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
                <paragraph><title_reference>Container Sync</title_reference> uses an internal client to GET objects that are to be sync’d.
                    This internal client must be configured to use the keymaster and encryption
                    middlewares as described <reference internal="True" refid="container-sync-client-config"><inline classes="std std-ref">above</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Encryption has no impact on the <title_reference>object-auditor</title_reference> service. Since the ETag
                    header saved with the object at rest is the md5 sum of the encrypted object
                    body then the auditor will verify that encrypted data is valid.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Encryption has no impact on the <title_reference>object-expirer</title_reference> service. <literal>X-Delete-At</literal> and
                    <literal>X-Delete-After</literal> headers are not encrypted.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Encryption has no impact on the <title_reference>object-replicator</title_reference> and <title_reference>object-reconstructor</title_reference>
                    services. These services are unaware of the object or EC fragment data being
                    encrypted.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Encryption has no impact on the <title_reference>container-reconciler</title_reference> service. The
                    <title_reference>container-reconciler</title_reference> uses an internal client to move objects between
                    different policy rings. The destination object has the same URL as the source
                    object and the object is moved without re-encryption.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="considerations-for-developers" names="considerations\ for\ developers">
                <title>Considerations for developers</title>
                <paragraph>Developers should be aware that keymaster and encryption middlewares rely on
                    the path of an object remaining unchanged. The included keymaster derives keys
                    for containers and objects based on their paths and the
                    <literal>encryption_root_secret</literal>. The keymaster does not rely on object metadata to
                    inform its generation of keys for GET and HEAD requests because when handling
                    <reference internal="True" refid="conditional-requests"><inline classes="std std-ref">Conditional Requests</inline></reference> it is required to provide the object key before any
                    metadata has been read from the object.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Developers should therefore give careful consideration to any new features that
                    would relocate object data and metadata within a Swift cluster by means that do
                    not cause the object data and metadata to pass through the encryption
                    middlewares in the proxy pipeline and be re-encrypted.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The crypto-metadata associated with each encrypted item does include some
                    <title_reference>key_id</title_reference> metadata that is provided by the keymaster and contains the path used
                    to derive keys. This <title_reference>key_id</title_reference> metadata is persisted in anticipation of future
                    scenarios when it may be necessary to decrypt an object that has been relocated
                    without re-encrypting, in which case the metadata could be used to derive the
                    keys that were used for encryption. However, this alone is not sufficient to
                    handle conditional requests and to decrypt container listings where objects
                    have been relocated, and further work will be required to solve those issues.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
