<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/horizon/doc/source/contributor/faq.rst">
    <target refid="faq"></target>
    <section ids="frequently-asked-questions faq" names="frequently\ asked\ questions faq">
        <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
        <paragraph>What is the relationship between <literal>Dashboards</literal>, <literal>Panels</literal>, and navigation?</paragraph>
        <block_quote>
            <paragraph>The navigational structure is strongly encouraged to flow from
                <literal>Dashboard</literal> objects as top-level navigation items to <literal>Panel</literal> objects as
                sub-navigation items as in the current implementation. Template tags
                are provided to automatically generate this structure.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>That said, you are not required to use the provided tools and can write
                templates and URLconfs by hand to create any desired structure.</paragraph>
        </block_quote>
        <paragraph>Does a panel have to be an app in <literal>INSTALLED_APPS</literal>?</paragraph>
        <block_quote>
            <paragraph>A panel can live in any Python module. It can be a standalone which ties
                into an existing dashboard, or it can be contained alongside others within
                a larger dashboard “app”. There is no strict enforcement here. Python
                is “a language for consenting adults.” A module containing a Panel does
                not need to be added to <literal>INSTALLED_APPS</literal>, but this is a common and
                convenient way to load a standalone panel.</paragraph>
        </block_quote>
        <paragraph>Could I hook an external service into a panel using, for example, an iFrame?</paragraph>
        <block_quote>
            <paragraph>Panels are just entry-points to hook views into the larger dashboard
                navigational structure and enforce common attributes like RBAC. The
                views and corresponding templates can contain anything you would like,
                including iFrames.</paragraph>
        </block_quote>
        <paragraph>What does this mean for visual design?</paragraph>
        <block_quote>
            <paragraph>The ability to add an arbitrary number of top-level navigational items
                (<literal>Dashboard</literal> objects) poses a new design challenge. Horizon’s lead
                designer has taken on the challenge of providing a reference design
                for Horizon which supports this possibility.</paragraph>
        </block_quote>
    </section>
</document>
