<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/nova/doc/source/admin/configuration/hypervisor-lxc.rst">
    <section ids="lxc-linux-containers" names="lxc\ (linux\ containers)">
        <title>LXC (Linux containers)</title>
        <paragraph>LXC (also known as Linux containers) is a virtualization technology that works
            at the operating system level. This is different from hardware virtualization,
            the approach used by other hypervisors such as KVM, Xen, and VMware. LXC (as
            currently implemented using libvirt in the Compute service) is not a secure
            virtualization technology for multi-tenant environments (specifically,
            containers may affect resource quotas for other containers hosted on the same
            machine). Additional containment technologies, such as AppArmor, may be used to
            provide better isolation between containers, although this is not the case by
            default.  For all these reasons, the choice of this virtualization technology
            is not recommended in production.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>If your compute hosts do not have hardware support for virtualization, LXC will
            likely provide better performance than QEMU. In addition, if your guests must
            access specialized hardware, such as GPUs, this might be easier to achieve with
            LXC than other hypervisors.</paragraph>
        <note>
            <paragraph>Some OpenStack Compute features might be missing when running with LXC as
                the hypervisor. See the <reference name="hypervisor support matrix" refuri="http://wiki.openstack.org/HypervisorSupportMatrix">hypervisor support matrix</reference><target ids="hypervisor-support-matrix" names="hypervisor\ support\ matrix" refuri="http://wiki.openstack.org/HypervisorSupportMatrix"></target> for details.</paragraph>
        </note>
        <paragraph>To enable LXC, ensure the following options are set in <literal>/etc/nova/nova.conf</literal>
            on all hosts running the <literal>nova-compute</literal> service.</paragraph>
        <literal_block highlight_args="{}" language="ini" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">compute_driver = libvirt.LibvirtDriver

[libvirt]
virt_type = lxc</literal_block>
        <paragraph>On Ubuntu, enable LXC support in OpenStack by installing the
            <literal>nova-compute-lxc</literal> package.</paragraph>
    </section>
</document>
