<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/manila/doc/source/admin/shared-file-systems-key-concepts.rst">
    <target refid="shared-file-systems-key-concepts"></target>
    <section ids="key-concepts shared-file-systems-key-concepts" names="key\ concepts shared_file_systems_key_concepts">
        <title>Key concepts</title>
        <section ids="share" names="share">
            <title>Share</title>
            <paragraph>In the Shared File Systems service <literal>share</literal> is the fundamental resource unit
                allocated by the Shared File System service. It represents an allocation of a
                persistent, readable, and writable filesystems. Compute instances access these
                filesystems. Depending on the deployment configuration, clients outside of
                OpenStack can also access the filesystem.</paragraph>
            <note>
                <paragraph>A <literal>share</literal> is an abstract storage object that may or may not directly
                    map to a “share” concept from the underlying storage provider.
                    See the description of <literal>share instance</literal> for more details.</paragraph>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section ids="share-instance" names="share\ instance">
            <title>Share instance</title>
            <paragraph>This concept is tied with <literal>share</literal> and represents created resource on specific
                back end, when <literal>share</literal> represents abstraction between end user and
                back-end storages. In common cases, it is one-to-one relation.
                One single <literal>share</literal> has more than one <literal>share instance</literal> in two cases:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>When <literal>share migration</literal> is being applied</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>When <literal>share replication</literal> is enabled</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>Therefore, each <literal>share instance</literal> stores information specific to real
                allocated resource on storage. And <literal>share</literal> represents the information
                that is common for <literal>share instances</literal>.
                A user with <literal>member</literal> role will not be able to work with it directly. Only
                a user with <literal>admin</literal> role has rights to perform actions against specific
                share instances.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="snapshot" names="snapshot">
            <title>Snapshot</title>
            <paragraph>A <literal>snapshot</literal> is a point-in-time, read-only copy of a <literal>share</literal>. You can
                create <literal>Snapshots</literal> from an existing, operational <literal>share</literal> regardless
                of whether a client has mounted the file system. A <literal>snapshot</literal>
                can serve as the content source for a new <literal>share</literal>. Specify the
                <strong>Create from snapshot</strong> option when creating a new <literal>share</literal> on the
                dashboard.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="storage-pools" names="storage\ pools">
            <title>Storage Pools</title>
            <paragraph>With the Kilo release of OpenStack, Shared File Systems can use
                <literal>storage pools</literal>. The storage may present one or more logical storage
                resource pools that the Shared File Systems service
                will select as a storage location when provisioning <literal>shares</literal>.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="share-type" names="share\ type">
            <title>Share Type</title>
            <paragraph><literal>Share type</literal> is an abstract collection of criteria used to characterize
                <literal>shares</literal>. They are most commonly used to create a hierarchy of functional
                capabilities. This hierarchy represents tiered storage services levels. For
                example, an administrator might define a premium <literal>share type</literal> that
                indicates a greater level of performance than a basic <literal>share type</literal>.
                Premium represents the best performance level.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="share-access-rules" names="share\ access\ rules">
            <title>Share Access Rules</title>
            <paragraph><literal>Share access rules</literal> define which users can access a particular <literal>share</literal>.
                For example, administrators can declare rules for NFS shares by
                listing the valid IP networks which will access the <literal>share</literal>. List the
                IP networks in CIDR notation.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="security-services" names="security\ services">
            <title>Security Services</title>
            <paragraph><literal>Security services``allow granular client access rules for
administrators. They can declare rules for authentication or
authorization to access ``share</literal> content. External services including LDAP,
                Active Directory, and Kerberos can be declared as resources. Examine and
                consult these resources when making an access decision for a
                particular <literal>share</literal>. You can associate <literal>Shares</literal> with multiple
                security services, but only one service per one type.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="share-networks" names="share\ networks">
            <title>Share Networks</title>
            <paragraph>A <literal>share network</literal> is an object that defines a relationship between a
                project network and subnet, as defined in an OpenStack Networking service or
                Compute service. The <literal>share network</literal> is also defined in <literal>shares</literal>
                created by the same project. A project may find it desirable to
                provision <literal>shares</literal> such that only instances connected to a particular
                OpenStack-defined network have access to the <literal>share</literal>. Also,
                <literal>security services</literal> can be attached to <literal>share networks</literal>,
                because most of auth protocols require some interaction with network services.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The Shared File Systems service has the ability to work outside of OpenStack.
                That is due to the <literal>StandaloneNetworkPlugin</literal>. The plugin is compatible with
                any network platform, and does not require specific network services in
                OpenStack like Compute or Networking service. You can set the network
                parameters in the <literal>manila.conf</literal> file.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="share-servers" names="share\ servers">
            <title>Share Servers</title>
            <paragraph>A <literal>share server</literal> is a logical entity that hosts the shares created
                on a specific <literal>share network</literal>. A <literal>share server</literal> may be a
                configuration object within the storage controller, or it may represent
                logical resources provisioned within an OpenStack deployment used to
                support the data path used to access <literal>shares</literal>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph><literal>Share servers</literal> interact with network services to determine the appropriate
                IP addresses on which to export <literal>shares</literal> according to the related <literal>share
network</literal>. The Shared File Systems service has a pluggable network model that
                allows <literal>share servers</literal> to work with different implementations of
                the Networking service.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
