<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/manila/doc/source/install/get-started-with-shared-file-systems.rst">
    <section ids="service-overview" names="service\ overview">
        <title>Service Overview</title>
        <paragraph>The OpenStack Shared File Systems service (manila) provides file storage to a
            virtual machine. The Shared File Systems service provides an abstraction
            for managing and provisioning of file shares. The service also enables
            management of share types as well as share snapshots if a driver supports
            them.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The Shared File Systems service consists of the following components:</paragraph>
        <definition_list>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-api</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>A WSGI app that authenticates and routes requests to the Shared File
                        Systems service.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-data</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>A standalone service whose purpose is to process data operations such as
                        copying, share migration or backup.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-scheduler</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>Schedules and routes requests to the appropriate share service. The
                        scheduler uses configurable filters and weighers to route requests. The
                        Filter Scheduler is the default and enables filters on various attributes
                        of back ends, such as, Capacity, Availability Zone and other capabilities.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>manila-share</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>Manages back-end devices that provide shared file systems. A manila-share
                        service talks to back-end devices by using share back-end drivers as
                        interfaces. A share driver may operate in one of two modes, with or
                        without handling of share servers. Share servers export file shares
                        via share networks. When share servers are not managed by a driver
                        within the shared file systems service, networking requirements should
                        be handled out of band of the shared file systems service.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
            <definition_list_item>
                <term>Messaging queue</term>
                <definition>
                    <paragraph>Routes information between the Shared File Systems processes.</paragraph>
                </definition>
            </definition_list_item>
        </definition_list>
        <paragraph>For more information, see <reference name="Configuration Reference Guide" refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/ocata/config-reference/shared-file-systems.html">Configuration Reference Guide</reference><target ids="configuration-reference-guide" names="configuration\ reference\ guide" refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/ocata/config-reference/shared-file-systems.html"></target>.</paragraph>
    </section>
</document>
