<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/glance/doc/source/user/formats.rst">
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright 2011 OpenStack Foundation
All Rights Reserved.

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain
a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.</comment>
    <target refid="formats"></target>
    <section ids="disk-and-container-formats formats" names="disk\ and\ container\ formats formats">
        <title>Disk and Container Formats</title>
        <paragraph>When adding an image to Glance, you must specify what the virtual
            machine image’s <emphasis>disk format</emphasis> and <emphasis>container format</emphasis> are. Disk and container
            formats are configurable on a per-deployment basis. This document intends to
            establish a global convention for what specific values of <emphasis>disk_format</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>container_format</emphasis> mean.</paragraph>
        <section ids="disk-format" names="disk\ format">
            <title>Disk Format</title>
            <paragraph>The disk format of a virtual machine image is the format of the underlying
                disk image. Virtual appliance vendors have different formats for laying out
                the information contained in a virtual machine disk image.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>You can set your image’s disk format to one of the following:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="*">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>raw</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This is an unstructured disk image format</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>vhd</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This is the VHD disk format, a common disk format used by virtual machine
                        monitors from VMware, Xen, Microsoft, VirtualBox, and others</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>vhdx</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This is the VHDX disk format, an enhanced version of the vhd format which
                        supports larger disk sizes among other features.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>vmdk</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>Another common disk format supported by many common virtual machine monitors</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>vdi</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>A disk format supported by VirtualBox virtual machine monitor and the QEMU
                        emulator</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>iso</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>An archive format for the data contents of an optical disc (e.g. CDROM).</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ploop</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>A disk format supported and used by Virtuozzo to run OS Containers</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>qcow2</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>A disk format supported by the QEMU emulator that can expand dynamically and
                        supports Copy on Write</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>aki</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an Amazon kernel image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ari</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an Amazon ramdisk image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ami</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an Amazon machine image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
        </section>
        <section ids="container-format" names="container\ format">
            <title>Container Format</title>
            <paragraph>The container format refers to whether the virtual machine image is in a
                file format that also contains metadata about the actual virtual machine.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Note that the container format string is not currently used by Glance or
                other OpenStack components, so it is safe to simply specify <strong>bare</strong> as
                the container format if you are unsure.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>You can set your image’s container format to one of the following:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="*">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>bare</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates there is no container or metadata envelope for the image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ovf</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This is the OVF container format</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>aki</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an Amazon kernel image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ari</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an Amazon ramdisk image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ami</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an Amazon machine image</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>ova</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is an OVA tar archive file</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>docker</strong></paragraph>
                    <paragraph>This indicates what is stored in Glance is a Docker tar archive of
                        the container filesystem</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
