<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/nova/doc/source/contributor/how-to-get-involved.rst">
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain
a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.</comment>
    <target refid="getting-involved"></target>
    <section ids="how-to-get-more-involved-with-nova getting-involved" names="how\ to\ get\ (more)\ involved\ with\ nova getting_involved">
        <title>How to get (more) involved with Nova</title>
        <paragraph>So you want to get more involved with Nova? Or you are new to Nova and
            wondering where to start?</paragraph>
        <paragraph>We are working on building easy ways for you to get help and ideas on
            how to learn more about Nova and how the Nova community works.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>Any questions, please ask! If you are unsure who to ask, then please
            contact the <reference anonymous="1" name="Mentoring Czar" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People">Mentoring Czar</reference>.</paragraph>
        <target anonymous="1" ids="id1" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People"></target>
        <section ids="how-do-i-get-started" names="how\ do\ i\ get\ started?">
            <title>How do I get started?</title>
            <paragraph>There are quite a few global docs on this:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><reference refuri="http://www.openstack.org/assets/welcome-guide/OpenStackWelcomeGuide.pdf">http://www.openstack.org/assets/welcome-guide/OpenStackWelcomeGuide.pdf</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/How_To_Contribute">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/How_To_Contribute</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><reference refuri="http://www.openstack.org/community/">http://www.openstack.org/community/</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>There is more general info, non Nova specific info here:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Mentors">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Mentors</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/OpenStack_Upstream_Training">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/OpenStack_Upstream_Training</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <section ids="what-should-i-work-on" names="what\ should\ i\ work\ on?">
                <title>What should I work on?</title>
                <paragraph>So you are starting out your Nova journey, where is a good place to
                    start?</paragraph>
                <paragraph>If you'd like to learn how Nova works before changing anything (good idea!), we
                    recommend looking for reviews with -1s and -2s and seeing why they got
                    downvoted. There is also the <reference internal="True" refuri="code-review#code-review"><inline classes="std std-ref">Code Review Guide for Nova</inline></reference>. Once you have some
                    understanding, start reviewing patches. It's OK to ask people to explain things
                    you don't understand. It's also OK to see some potential problems but put a +0.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Another way is to look for a subteam you'd like to get involved with and review
                    their patches. See:
                    <reference refuri="https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/pike-nova-priorities-tracking">https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/pike-nova-priorities-tracking</reference></paragraph>
                <paragraph>Once you're ready to write code, take a look at some of the work already marked
                    as low-hanging fruit:</paragraph>
                <bullet_list bullet="*">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph><reference refuri="https://bugs.launchpad.net/nova/+bugs?field.tag=low-hanging-fruit">https://bugs.launchpad.net/nova/+bugs?field.tag=low-hanging-fruit</reference></paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph><reference refuri="https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/nova-low-hanging-fruit">https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/nova-low-hanging-fruit</reference></paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </bullet_list>
            </section>
            <section ids="how-do-i-get-my-feature-in" names="how\ do\ i\ get\ my\ feature\ in?">
                <title>How do I get my feature in?</title>
                <paragraph>The best way of getting your feature in is... well it depends.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>First concentrate on solving your problem and/or use case, don't fixate
                    on getting the code you have working merged. It's likely things will need
                    significant re-work after you discuss how your needs match up with all
                    the existing ways Nova is currently being used. The good news, is this
                    process should leave you with a feature that's more flexible and doesn't
                    lock you into your current way of thinking.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>A key part of getting code merged, is helping with reviewing other
                    people's code. Great reviews of others code will help free up more core
                    reviewer time to look at your own patches. In addition, you will
                    understand how the review is thinking when they review your code.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Also, work out if any on going efforts are blocking your feature and
                    helping out speeding those up. The spec review process should help with
                    this effort.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>For more details on our process, please see: <reference internal="True" refuri="process#process"><inline classes="std std-ref">Nova team process</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="what-is-expected-of-a-good-contributor" names="what\ is\ expected\ of\ a\ good\ contributor?">
                <title>What is expected of a good contributor?</title>
                <paragraph>TODO - need more info on this</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section ids="top-tips-for-working-with-the-nova-community" names="top\ tips\ for\ working\ with\ the\ nova\ community">
            <title>Top Tips for working with the Nova community</title>
            <paragraph>Here are some top tips around engaging with the Nova community:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>IRC</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>we talk a lot in #openstack-nova</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>do ask us questions in there, and we will try to help you</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>not sure about asking questions? feel free to listen in around
                                other people's questions</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>we recommend you setup an IRC bouncer:
                                <reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/IRC">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/IRC</reference></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Email</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Use the [nova] tag in the mailing lists</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Filtering on [nova] and [all] can help tame the list</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Be Open</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>i.e. don't review your teams code in private, do it publicly in
                                gerrit</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>i.e. be ready to talk about openly about problems you are having,
                                not "theoretical" issues</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>that way you can start to gain the trust of the wider community</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Got a problem? Please ask!</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Please raise any problems and ask questions early</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>we want to help you before you are frustrated or annoyed</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>unsure who to ask? Just ask in IRC, or check out the list of <reference name="Nova people" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People">Nova
                                    people</reference>.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Talk about problems first, then solutions</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Nova is a big project. At first, it can be hard to see the big
                                picture</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Don't think about "merging your patch", instead think about
                                "solving your problem"</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>conversations are more productive that way</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>It's not the decision that's important, it's the reason behind it that's
                        important</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Don't like the way the community is going?</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Please ask why we were going that way, and please engage with the
                                debate</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>If you don't, we are unable to learn from what you have to offer</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>No one will decide, this is stuck, who can help me?</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>it's rare, but it happens</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>it's the <reference anonymous="1" name="Nova PTL" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People">Nova PTL</reference>'s job to help you</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>...but if you don't ask, it's hard for them to help you</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <target anonymous="1" ids="id2" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="process" names="process">
            <title>Process</title>
            <paragraph>It can feel like you are faced with a wall of process. We are a big
                community, to make sure the right communication happens, we do use a
                minimal amount of process.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>If you find something that doesn't make sense, please:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>ask questions to find out *why* it happens</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>if you know of a better way to do it, please speak up</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>one "better way" might be to remove the process if it no longer helps</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>To learn more about Nova's process, please read <reference internal="True" refuri="process#process"><inline classes="std std-ref">Nova team process</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
            <section ids="why-bother-with-any-process" names="why\ bother\ with\ any\ process?">
                <title>Why bother with any process?</title>
                <paragraph>Why is it worth creating a bug or blueprint to track your code review?
                    This may seem like silly process, but there is usually a good reason
                    behind it.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>We have lots of code to review, and we have tools to try and get to
                    really important code reviews first. If yours is really important, but
                    not picked up by our tools, it's possible you just get lost in the bottom
                    of a big queue.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>If you have a bug fix, you have done loads of work to identify the
                    issue, and test out your fix, and submit it. By adding a bug report, you
                    are making it easier for other folks who hit the same problem to find
                    your work, possibly saving them the hours of pain you went through. With
                    any luck that gives all those people the time to fix different bugs, all
                    that might have affected you, if you had not given them the time go fix
                    it.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>It's similar with blueprints. You have worked out how to scratch your
                    itch, lets tell others about that great new feature you have added, so
                    they can use that. Also, it stops someone with a similar idea going
                    through all the pain of creating a feature only to find you already have
                    that feature ready and up for review, or merged into the latest release.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Hopefully this gives you an idea why we have applied a small layer of
                    process to what we are doing. Having said all this, we need to unlearn
                    old habits to move forward, there may be better ways to do things, and
                    we are open to trying them. Please help be part of the solution.</paragraph>
                <target refid="why-plus1"></target>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section ids="why-do-code-reviews-if-i-am-not-in-nova-core why-plus1" names="why\ do\ code\ reviews\ if\ i\ am\ not\ in\ nova-core? why_plus1">
            <title>Why do code reviews if I am not in nova-core?</title>
            <paragraph>Code reviews are the life blood of the Nova developer community.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>There is a good discussion on how you do good reviews, and how anyone
                can be a reviewer:
                <reference refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/infra/manual/developers.html#peer-review">http://docs.openstack.org/infra/manual/developers.html#peer-review</reference></paragraph>
            <paragraph>In the draft process guide, I discuss how doing reviews can help get
                your code merged faster: <reference internal="True" refuri="process#process"><inline classes="std std-ref">Nova team process</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Lets look at some of the top reasons why participating with code reviews
                really helps you:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Doing more reviews, and seeing what other reviewers notice, will help
                        you better understand what is expected of code that gets merged into
                        master</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Having more non-core people do great reviews, leaves less review work
                        for the core reviewers to do, so we are able get more code merged</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Empathy is one of the keys to a happy community. If you are used to
                        doing code reviews, you will better understand the comments you get
                        when people review your code. As you do more code reviews, and see
                        what others notice, you will get a better idea of what people are
                        looking for when then apply a +2 to your code.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>TODO - needs more detail</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>What are the most useful types of code review comments? Well here are a
                few to the top ones:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Fundamental flaws are the biggest thing to spot. Does the patch break
                        a whole set of existing users, or an existing feature?</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Consistency of behaviour is really important. Does this bit of code
                        do things differently to where similar things happen else where in
                        Nova?</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Is the code easy to maintain, well tested and easy to read? Code is
                        read order of magnitude times more than it is written, so optimise
                        for the reader of the code, not the writer.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>TODO - what others should go here?</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>Let's look at some problems people hit when starting out doing code
                reviews:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>My +1 doesn't mean anything, why should I bother?</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>So your +1 really does help. Some really useful -1 votes that lead
                                to a +1 vote helps get code into a position</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>When to use -1 vs 0 vs +1</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Please see the guidelines here:
                                <reference refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/infra/manual/developers.html#peer-review">http://docs.openstack.org/infra/manual/developers.html#peer-review</reference></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>I have already reviewed this code internally, no point in adding a +1
                        externally?</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Please talk to your company about doing all code reviews in the
                                public, that is a much better way to get involved. showing how the
                                code has evolved upstream, is much better than trying to 'perfect'
                                code internally, before uploading for public review. You can use
                                Draft mode, and mark things as WIP if you prefer, but please do
                                the reviews upstream.</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Where do I start? What should I review?</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>There are various tools, but a good place to start is:
                                <reference refuri="https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/pike-nova-priorities-tracking">https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/pike-nova-priorities-tracking</reference></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Depending on the time in the cycle, it's worth looking at
                                NeedsCodeReview blueprints:
                                <reference refuri="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/nova/">https://blueprints.launchpad.net/nova/</reference></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Custom Gerrit review dashboards often provide a more manageable view of
                                the outstanding reviews, and help focus your efforts:</paragraph>
                            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                                <list_item>
                                    <paragraph>Nova Review Inbox:
                                        <reference refuri="https://goo.gl/1vTS0Z">https://goo.gl/1vTS0Z</reference></paragraph>
                                </list_item>
                                <list_item>
                                    <paragraph>Small Bug Fixes:
                                        <reference refuri="http://ow.ly/WAw1J">http://ow.ly/WAw1J</reference></paragraph>
                                </list_item>
                            </bullet_list>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Maybe take a look at things you want to see merged, bug fixes and
                                features, or little code fixes</paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>Look for things that have been waiting a long time for a review:
                                <reference refuri="http://5885fef486164bb8596d-41634d3e64ee11f37e8658ed1b4d12ec.r44.cf3.rackcdn.com/nova-openreviews.html">http://5885fef486164bb8596d-41634d3e64ee11f37e8658ed1b4d12ec.r44.cf3.rackcdn.com/nova-openreviews.html</reference></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph>If you get through the above lists, try other tools, such as:
                                <reference refuri="http://status.openstack.org/reviews">http://status.openstack.org/reviews</reference></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
        </section>
        <section ids="how-to-do-great-code-reviews" names="how\ to\ do\ great\ code\ reviews?">
            <title>How to do great code reviews?</title>
            <paragraph><reference refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/infra/manual/developers.html#peer-review">http://docs.openstack.org/infra/manual/developers.html#peer-review</reference></paragraph>
            <paragraph>For more tips, please see: <reference name="Why do code reviews if I am not in nova-core?" refid="why-do-code-reviews-if-i-am-not-in-nova-core">Why do code reviews if I am not in nova-core?</reference></paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="how-do-i-become-nova-core" names="how\ do\ i\ become\ nova-core?">
            <title>How do I become nova-core?</title>
            <paragraph>You don't have to be nova-core to be a valued member of the Nova
                community. There are many, many ways you can help. Every quality review
                that helps someone get their patch closer to being ready to merge helps
                everyone get their code merged faster.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The first step to becoming nova-core is learning how to be an active
                member of the Nova community, including learning how to do great code
                reviews. For more details see:
                <reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/CoreTeam#Membership_Expectations">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/CoreTeam#Membership_Expectations</reference></paragraph>
            <paragraph>If you feel like you have the time to commit to all the nova-core
                membership expectations, reach out to the Nova PTL who will be
                able to find you an existing member of nova-core to help mentor you. If
                all goes well, and you seem like a good candidate, your mentor will
                contact the rest of the nova-core team to ask them to start looking at
                your reviews, so they are able to vote for you, if you get nominated for
                join nova-core.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>We encourage all mentoring, where possible, to occur on #openstack-nova
                so everyone can learn and benefit from your discussions.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The above mentoring is available to every one who wants to learn how to
                better code reviews, even if you don't ever want to commit to becoming
                nova-core. If you already have a mentor, that's great, the process is
                only there for folks who are still trying to find a mentor. Being
                admitted to the mentoring program no way guarantees you will become a
                member of nova-core eventually, it's here to help you improve, and help
                you have the sort of involvement and conversations that can lead to
                becoming a member of nova-core.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="how-to-do-great-nova-spec-reviews" names="how\ to\ do\ great\ nova-spec\ reviews?">
            <title>How to do great nova-spec reviews?</title>
            <paragraph><reference refuri="http://specs.openstack.org/openstack/nova-specs/specs/ocata/template.html">http://specs.openstack.org/openstack/nova-specs/specs/ocata/template.html</reference></paragraph>
            <paragraph><reference refuri="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/nova/blueprints.html#specs">http://docs.openstack.org/developer/nova/blueprints.html#specs</reference></paragraph>
            <paragraph>Spec reviews are always a step ahead of the normal code reviews. Follow
                the above links for some great information on specs/reviews.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The following could be some important tips:</paragraph>
            <paragraph>1. The specs are published as html documents. Ensure that the author has
                a proper render of the same via the .rst file.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>2. More often than not, it's important to know that there are no
                overlaps across multiple specs.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>3. Ensure that a proper dependency of the spec is identified. For
                example - a user desired feature that requires a proper base enablement
                should be a dependent spec.</paragraph>
            <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" start="4" suffix=".">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Ask for clarity on changes that appear ambiguous to you.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </enumerated_list>
            <paragraph>5. Every release nova gets a huge set of spec proposals and that's a
                huge task for the limited set of nova cores to complete. Helping the
                cores with additional reviews is always a great thing.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="how-to-do-great-bug-triage" names="how\ to\ do\ great\ bug\ triage?">
            <title>How to do great bug triage?</title>
            <paragraph><reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/BugTriage">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/BugTriage</reference></paragraph>
            <paragraph>More details coming soon...</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="how-to-step-up-into-a-project-leadership-role" names="how\ to\ step\ up\ into\ a\ project\ leadership\ role?">
            <title>How to step up into a project leadership role?</title>
            <paragraph>There are many ways to help lead the Nova project:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="*">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Mentoring efforts, and getting started tips:
                        <reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/Mentoring">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/Mentoring</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Info on process, with a focus on how you can go from an idea
                        to getting code merged Nova:
                        <reference refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/Mitaka_Release_Schedule">https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/Mitaka_Release_Schedule</reference></paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Consider leading an existing <reference name="Nova subteam" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#Nova_subteams">Nova subteam</reference> or forming a new one.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Consider becoming a <reference name="Bug tag owner" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/BugTriage#Step_2:_Triage_Tagged_Bugs">Bug tag owner</reference>.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Contact the PTL about becoming a Czar <reference name="Nova People" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People">Nova People</reference>.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <target ids="nova-people" names="nova\ people" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#People"></target>
            <target ids="nova-subteam" names="nova\ subteam" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova#Nova_subteams"></target>
            <target ids="bug-tag-owner" names="bug\ tag\ owner" refuri="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Nova/BugTriage#Step_2:_Triage_Tagged_Bugs"></target>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
