<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/swift/doc/source/admin/objectstorage-EC.rst">
    <section ids="erasure-coding" names="erasure\ coding">
        <title>Erasure coding</title>
        <paragraph>Erasure coding is a set of algorithms that allows the reconstruction of
            missing data from a set of original data. In theory, erasure coding uses
            less capacity with similar durability characteristics as replicas.
            From an application perspective, erasure coding support is transparent.
            Object Storage (swift) implements erasure coding as a Storage Policy.
            See <reference internal="True" refuri="../overview_policies"><inline classes="doc">Storage Policies</inline></reference> for more details.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>There is no external API related to erasure coding. Create a container using a
            Storage Policy; the interaction with the cluster is the same as any
            other durability policy. Because support implements as a Storage Policy,
            you can isolate all storage devices that associate with your cluster’s
            erasure coding capability. It is entirely possible to share devices between
            storage policies, but for erasure coding it may make more sense to use
            not only separate devices but possibly even entire nodes dedicated for erasure
            coding.</paragraph>
        <important>
            <paragraph>The erasure code support in Object Storage is considered beta in Kilo.
                Most major functionality is included, but it has not been tested or
                validated at large scale. This feature relies on <literal>ssync</literal> for durability.
                We recommend deployers do extensive testing and not deploy production
                data using an erasure code storage policy.
                If any bugs are found during testing, please report them to
                <reference refuri="https://bugs.launchpad.net/swift">https://bugs.launchpad.net/swift</reference></paragraph>
        </important>
    </section>
</document>
