<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/swift/doc/source/admin/objectstorage-large-objects.rst">
    <section ids="large-object-support" names="large\ object\ support">
        <title>Large object support</title>
        <paragraph>Object Storage (swift) uses segmentation to support the upload of large
            objects. By default, Object Storage limits the download size of a single
            object to 5GB. Using segmentation, uploading a single object is virtually
            unlimited. The segmentation process works by fragmenting the object,
            and automatically creating a file that sends the segments together as
            a single object. This option offers greater upload speed with the possibility
            of parallel uploads.</paragraph>
        <section ids="large-objects" names="large\ objects">
            <title>Large objects</title>
            <paragraph>The large object is comprised of two types of objects:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><strong>Segment objects</strong> store the object content. You can divide your
                        content into segments, and upload each segment into its own segment
                        object. Segment objects do not have any special features. You create,
                        update, download, and delete segment objects just as you would normal
                        objects.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>A <strong>manifest object</strong> links the segment objects into one logical
                        large object. When you download a manifest object, Object Storage
                        concatenates and returns the contents of the segment objects in the
                        response body of the request. The manifest object types are:</paragraph>
                    <bullet_list bullet="-">
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph><strong>Static large objects</strong></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                        <list_item>
                            <paragraph><strong>Dynamic large objects</strong></paragraph>
                        </list_item>
                    </bullet_list>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>To find out more information on large object support,
                see <reference internal="True" refuri="../overview_large_objects"><inline classes="doc">Large Object Support</inline></reference> in the developer documentation.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
