<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/swift/doc/source/admin/objectstorage-arch.rst">
    <section ids="cluster-architecture" names="cluster\ architecture">
        <title>Cluster architecture</title>
        <section ids="access-tier" names="access\ tier">
            <title>Access tier</title>
            <paragraph>Large-scale deployments segment off an access tier, which is considered
                the Object Storage system’s central hub. The access tier fields the
                incoming API requests from clients and moves data in and out of the
                system. This tier consists of front-end load balancers, ssl-terminators,
                and authentication services. It runs the (distributed) brain of the
                Object Storage system: the proxy server processes.</paragraph>
            <note>
                <paragraph>If you want to use OpenStack Identity API v3 for authentication, you
                    have the following options available in <literal>/etc/swift/dispersion.conf</literal>:
                    <literal>auth_version</literal>, <literal>user_domain_name</literal>, <literal>project_domain_name</literal>,
                    and <literal>project_name</literal>.</paragraph>
            </note>
            <paragraph><strong>Object Storage architecture</strong></paragraph>
            <figure>
                <image candidates="{'*': u'admin/figures/objectstorage-arch.png'}" uri="admin/figures/objectstorage-arch.png"></image>
            </figure>
            <paragraph>Because access servers are collocated in their own tier, you can scale
                out read/write access regardless of the storage capacity. For example,
                if a cluster is on the public Internet, requires SSL termination, and
                has a high demand for data access, you can provision many access
                servers. However, if the cluster is on a private network and used
                primarily for archival purposes, you need fewer access servers.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Since this is an HTTP addressable storage service, you may incorporate a
                load balancer into the access tier.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Typically, the tier consists of a collection of 1U servers. These
                machines use a moderate amount of RAM and are network I/O intensive.
                Since these systems field each incoming API request, you should
                provision them with two high-throughput (10GbE) interfaces - one for the
                incoming front-end requests and the other for the back-end access to
                the object storage nodes to put and fetch data.</paragraph>
            <section dupnames="factors\ to\ consider" ids="factors-to-consider">
                <title>Factors to consider</title>
                <paragraph>For most publicly facing deployments as well as private deployments
                    available across a wide-reaching corporate network, you use SSL to
                    encrypt traffic to the client. SSL adds significant processing load to
                    establish sessions between clients, which is why you have to provision
                    more capacity in the access layer. SSL may not be required for private
                    deployments on trusted networks.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section ids="storage-nodes" names="storage\ nodes">
            <title>Storage nodes</title>
            <paragraph>In most configurations, each of the five zones should have an equal
                amount of storage capacity. Storage nodes use a reasonable amount of
                memory and CPU. Metadata needs to be readily available to return objects
                quickly. The object stores run services not only to field incoming
                requests from the access tier, but to also run replicators, auditors,
                and reapers. You can provision storage nodes with single gigabit or
                10 gigabit network interface depending on the expected workload and
                desired performance, although it may be desirable to isolate replication
                traffic with a second interface.</paragraph>
            <paragraph><strong>Object Storage (swift)</strong></paragraph>
            <figure>
                <image candidates="{'*': u'admin/figures/objectstorage-nodes.png'}" uri="admin/figures/objectstorage-nodes.png"></image>
            </figure>
            <paragraph>Currently, a 2 TB or 3 TB SATA disk delivers good performance for the
                price. You can use desktop-grade drives if you have responsive remote
                hands in the datacenter and enterprise-grade drives if you don’t.</paragraph>
            <section dupnames="factors\ to\ consider" ids="id1">
                <title>Factors to consider</title>
                <paragraph>You should keep in mind the desired I/O performance for single-threaded
                    requests. This system does not use RAID, so a single disk handles each
                    request for an object. Disk performance impacts single-threaded response
                    rates.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>To achieve apparent higher throughput, the object storage system is
                    designed to handle concurrent uploads/downloads. The network I/O
                    capacity (1GbE, bonded 1GbE pair, or 10GbE) should match your desired
                    concurrent throughput needs for reads and writes.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
