<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/swift/doc/source/admin/objectstorage-monitoring.rst">
    <section ids="object-storage-monitoring" names="object\ storage\ monitoring">
        <title>Object Storage monitoring</title>
        <note>
            <paragraph>This section was excerpted from a <reference name="blog post by Darrell Bishop" refuri="http://swiftstack.com/blog/2012/04/11/swift-monitoring-with-statsd">blog post by Darrell
                    Bishop</reference><target ids="blog-post-by-darrell-bishop" names="blog\ post\ by\ darrell\ bishop" refuri="http://swiftstack.com/blog/2012/04/11/swift-monitoring-with-statsd"></target> and
                has since been edited.</paragraph>
        </note>
        <paragraph>An OpenStack Object Storage cluster is a collection of many daemons that
            work together across many nodes. With so many different components, you
            must be able to tell what is going on inside the cluster. Tracking
            server-level meters like CPU utilization, load, memory consumption, disk
            usage and utilization, and so on is necessary, but not sufficient.</paragraph>
        <section ids="swift-recon" names="swift\ recon">
            <title>Swift Recon</title>
            <paragraph>The Swift Recon middleware (see <reference internal="True" refuri="../admin_guide#cluster-telemetry-and-monitoring"><inline classes="std std-ref">Cluster Telemetry and Monitoring</inline></reference>)
                provides general machine statistics, such as load average, socket
                statistics, <literal>/proc/meminfo</literal> contents, as well as Swift-specific meters:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>The <literal>MD5</literal> sum of each ring file.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>The most recent object replication time.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Count of each type of quarantined file: Account, container, or
                        object.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Count of “async_pendings” (deferred container updates) on disk.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>Swift Recon is middleware that is installed in the object servers
                pipeline and takes one required option: A local cache directory. To
                track <literal>async_pendings</literal>, you must set up an additional cron job for
                each object server. You access data by either sending HTTP requests
                directly to the object server or using the <literal>swift-recon</literal> command-line
                client.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>There are Object Storage cluster statistics but the typical
                server meters overlap with existing server monitoring systems. To get
                the Swift-specific meters into a monitoring system, they must be polled.
                Swift Recon acts as a middleware meters collector. The
                process that feeds meters to your statistics system, such as
                <literal>collectd</literal> and <literal>gmond</literal>, should already run on the storage node.
                You can choose to either talk to Swift Recon or collect the meters
                directly.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section dupnames="swift-informant" ids="swift-informant">
            <title>Swift-Informant</title>
            <paragraph>Swift-Informant middleware (see
                <reference name="swift-informant" refuri="https://github.com/pandemicsyn/swift-informant">swift-informant</reference><target ids="id1" names="swift-informant" refuri="https://github.com/pandemicsyn/swift-informant"></target>) has
                real-time visibility into Object Storage client requests. It sits in the
                pipeline for the proxy server, and after each request to the proxy server it
                sends three meters to a <literal>StatsD</literal> server:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>A counter increment for a meter like <literal>obj.GET.200</literal> or
                        <literal>cont.PUT.404</literal>.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Timing data for a meter like <literal>acct.GET.200</literal> or <literal>obj.GET.200</literal>.
                        [The README says the meters look like <literal>duration.acct.GET.200</literal>, but
                        I do not see the <literal>duration</literal> in the code. I am not sure what the
                        Etsy server does but our StatsD server turns timing meters into five
                        derivative meters with new segments appended, so it probably works as
                        coded. The first meter turns into <literal>acct.GET.200.lower</literal>,
                        <literal>acct.GET.200.upper</literal>, <literal>acct.GET.200.mean</literal>,
                        <literal>acct.GET.200.upper_90</literal>, and <literal>acct.GET.200.count</literal>].</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>A counter increase by the bytes transferred for a meter like
                        <literal>tfer.obj.PUT.201</literal>.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>This is used for receiving information on the quality of service clients
                experience with the timing meters, as well as sensing the volume of the
                various modifications of a request server type, command, and response
                code. Swift-Informant requires no change to core Object
                Storage code because it is implemented as middleware. However, it gives
                no insight into the workings of the cluster past the proxy server.
                If the responsiveness of one storage node degrades, you can only see
                that some of the requests are bad, either as high latency or error
                status codes.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section dupnames="statsdlog" ids="statsdlog">
            <title>Statsdlog</title>
            <paragraph>The <reference name="Statsdlog" refuri="https://github.com/pandemicsyn/statsdlog">Statsdlog</reference><target ids="id2" names="statsdlog" refuri="https://github.com/pandemicsyn/statsdlog"></target>
                project increments StatsD counters based on logged events. Like
                Swift-Informant, it is also non-intrusive, however statsdlog can track
                events from all Object Storage daemons, not just proxy-server. The
                daemon listens to a UDP stream of syslog messages, and StatsD counters
                are incremented when a log line matches a regular expression. Meter
                names are mapped to regex match patterns in a JSON file, allowing
                flexible configuration of what meters are extracted from the log stream.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Currently, only the first matching regex triggers a StatsD counter
                increment, and the counter is always incremented by one. There is no way
                to increment a counter by more than one or send timing data to StatsD
                based on the log line content. The tool could be extended to handle more
                meters for each line and data extraction, including timing data. But a
                coupling would still exist between the log textual format and the log
                parsing regexes, which would themselves be more complex to support
                multiple matches for each line and data extraction. Also, log processing
                introduces a delay between the triggering event and sending the data to
                StatsD. It would be preferable to increment error counters where they
                occur and send timing data as soon as it is known to avoid coupling
                between a log string and a parsing regex and prevent a time delay
                between events and sending data to StatsD.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The next section describes another method for gathering Object Storage
                operational meters.</paragraph>
        </section>
        <section ids="swift-statsd-logging" names="swift\ statsd\ logging">
            <title>Swift StatsD logging</title>
            <paragraph>StatsD (see <reference name="Measure Anything, Measure Everything" refuri="http://codeascraft.etsy.com/2011/02/15/measure-anything-measure-everything/">Measure Anything, Measure Everything</reference><target ids="measure-anything-measure-everything" names="measure\ anything,\ measure\ everything" refuri="http://codeascraft.etsy.com/2011/02/15/measure-anything-measure-everything/"></target>)
                was designed for application code to be deeply instrumented. Meters are
                sent in real-time by the code that just noticed or did something. The
                overhead of sending a meter is extremely low: a <literal>sendto</literal> of one UDP
                packet. If that overhead is still too high, the StatsD client library
                can send only a random portion of samples and StatsD approximates the
                actual number when flushing meters upstream.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>To avoid the problems inherent with middleware-based monitoring and
                after-the-fact log processing, the sending of StatsD meters is
                integrated into Object Storage itself. The submitted change set (see
                <reference name="https://review.openstack.org/#change,6058" refuri="https://review.openstack.org/#change,6058">https://review.openstack.org/#change,6058</reference><target ids="https-review-openstack-org-change-6058" names="https://review.openstack.org/#change,6058" refuri="https://review.openstack.org/#change,6058"></target>) currently reports 124 meters
                across 15 Object Storage daemons and the tempauth middleware. Details of
                the meters tracked are in the <reference internal="True" refuri="../admin_guide"><inline classes="doc">Administrator’s Guide</inline></reference>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The sending of meters is integrated with the logging framework. To
                enable, configure <literal>log_statsd_host</literal> in the relevant config file. You
                can also specify the port and a default sample rate. The specified
                default sample rate is used unless a specific call to a statsd logging
                method (see the list below) overrides it. Currently, no logging calls
                override the sample rate, but it is conceivable that some meters may
                require accuracy (<literal>sample_rate=1</literal>) while others may not.</paragraph>
            <literal_block highlight_args="{}" language="ini" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve">[DEFAULT]
# ...
log_statsd_host = 127.0.0.1
log_statsd_port = 8125
log_statsd_default_sample_rate = 1</literal_block>
            <paragraph>Then the LogAdapter object returned by <literal>get_logger()</literal>, usually stored
                in <literal>self.logger</literal>, has these new methods:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><literal>set_statsd_prefix(self, prefix)</literal> Sets the client library stat
                        prefix value which gets prefixed to every meter. The default prefix
                        is the <literal>name</literal> of the logger such as <literal>object-server</literal>,
                        <literal>container-auditor</literal>, and so on. This is currently used to turn
                        <literal>proxy-server</literal> into one of <literal>proxy-server.Account</literal>,
                        <literal>proxy-server.Container</literal>, or <literal>proxy-server.Object</literal> as soon as the
                        Controller object is determined and instantiated for the request.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><literal>update_stats(self, metric, amount, sample_rate=1)</literal> Increments
                        the supplied meter by the given amount. This is used when you need
                        to add or subtract more that one from a counter, like incrementing
                        <literal>suffix.hashes</literal> by the number of computed hashes in the object
                        replicator.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><literal>increment(self, metric, sample_rate=1)</literal> Increments the given counter
                        meter by one.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><literal>decrement(self, metric, sample_rate=1)</literal> Lowers the given counter
                        meter by one.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><literal>timing(self, metric, timing_ms, sample_rate=1)</literal> Record that the
                        given meter took the supplied number of milliseconds.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph><literal>timing_since(self, metric, orig_time, sample_rate=1)</literal>
                        Convenience method to record a timing meter whose value is “now”
                        minus an existing timestamp.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <note>
                <paragraph>These logging methods may safely be called anywhere you have a
                    logger object. If StatsD logging has not been configured, the methods
                    are no-ops. This avoids messy conditional logic each place a meter is
                    recorded. These example usages show the new logging methods:</paragraph>
                <literal_block highlight_args="{}" language="python" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve"># swift/obj/replicator.py
def update(self, job):
     # ...
    begin = time.time()
    try:
        hashed, local_hash = tpool.execute(tpooled_get_hashes, job['path'],
                do_listdir=(self.replication_count % 10) == 0,
                reclaim_age=self.reclaim_age)
        # See tpooled_get_hashes "Hack".
        if isinstance(hashed, BaseException):
            raise hashed
        self.suffix_hash += hashed
        self.logger.update_stats('suffix.hashes', hashed)
        # ...
    finally:
        self.partition_times.append(time.time() - begin)
        self.logger.timing_since('partition.update.timing', begin)</literal_block>
                <literal_block highlight_args="{}" language="python" linenos="False" xml:space="preserve"># swift/container/updater.py
def process_container(self, dbfile):
    # ...
    start_time = time.time()
    # ...
        for event in events:
            if 200 &lt;= event.wait() &lt; 300:
                successes += 1
            else:
                failures += 1
        if successes &gt; failures:
          self.logger.increment('successes')
            # ...
        else:
            self.logger.increment('failures')
            # ...
        # Only track timing data for attempted updates:
        self.logger.timing_since('timing', start_time)
    else:
        self.logger.increment('no_changes')
        self.no_changes += 1</literal_block>
            </note>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
