<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/neutron/doc/source/contributor/internals/db_models.rst">
    <comment xml:space="preserve">Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may
not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain
a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.</comment>
    <section ids="relocation-of-database-models" names="relocation\ of\ database\ models">
        <title>Relocation of Database Models</title>
        <paragraph>This document is intended to track and notify developers that db models in
            neutron will be centralized and moved to a new tree under neutron/db/models.
            This was discussed in [1]. The reason for relocating db models is to solve
            the cyclic import issue while implementing oslo versioned objects for
            resources in neutron.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The reason behind this relocation is Mixin class and db models for some
            resources in neutron are in same module. In Mixin classes, there are methods
            which provide functionality of fetching, adding, updating and deleting data
            via queries. These queries will be replaced with use of versioned objects and
            definition of versioned object will be using db models. So object files will
            be importing models and Mixin need to import those objects which will end up
            in cyclic import.</paragraph>
        <section ids="structure-of-model-definitions" names="structure\ of\ model\ definitions">
            <title>Structure of Model Definitions</title>
            <paragraph>We have decided to move all models definitions to neutron/db/models/
                with no further nesting after that point. The deprecation method to move
                models has already been added to avoid breakage of third party plugins using
                those models. All relocated models need to use deprecate method that
                will generate a warning and return new class for use of old class. Some
                examples of relocated models [2] and [3]. In future if you define new models
                please make sure they are separated from mixins and are under tree
                neutron/db/models/ .</paragraph>
            <section ids="references" names="references">
                <title>References</title>
                <paragraph>[1]. <reference refuri="https://www.mail-archive.com/openstack-dev@lists.openstack.org/msg88910.html">https://www.mail-archive.com/openstack-dev@lists.openstack.org/msg88910.html</reference>
                    [2]. <reference refuri="https://review.openstack.org/#/c/348562/">https://review.openstack.org/#/c/348562/</reference>
                    [3]. <reference refuri="https://review.openstack.org/#/c/348757/">https://review.openstack.org/#/c/348757/</reference></paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
