<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document source="/home/fbaumanis/openstack/soc8_test/openstack_repo/nova/doc/source/install/overview.rst">
    <section ids="overview" names="overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <paragraph>The OpenStack project is an open source cloud computing platform that supports
            all types of cloud environments. The project aims for simple implementation,
            massive scalability, and a rich set of features. Cloud computing experts from
            around the world contribute to the project.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>OpenStack provides an Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) solution through a
            variety of complementary services. Each service offers an Application
            Programming Interface (API) that facilitates this integration.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>This guide covers step-by-step deployment of the major OpenStack services using
            a functional example architecture suitable for new users of OpenStack with
            sufficient Linux experience. This guide is not intended to be used for
            production system installations, but to create a minimum proof-of-concept for
            the purpose of learning about OpenStack.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>After becoming familiar with basic installation, configuration, operation, and
            troubleshooting of these OpenStack services, you should consider the following
            steps toward deployment using a production architecture:</paragraph>
        <bullet_list bullet="*">
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Determine and implement the necessary core and optional services to meet
                    performance and redundancy requirements.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Increase security using methods such as firewalls, encryption, and service
                    policies.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
            <list_item>
                <paragraph>Implement a deployment tool such as Ansible, Chef, Puppet, or Salt to
                    automate deployment and management of the production environment.</paragraph>
            </list_item>
        </bullet_list>
        <target refid="overview-example-architectures"></target>
        <section ids="example-architecture overview-example-architectures" names="example\ architecture overview-example-architectures">
            <title>Example architecture</title>
            <paragraph>The example architecture requires at least two nodes (hosts) to launch a basic
                virtual machine (VM) or instance. Optional services such as Block Storage and
                Object Storage require additional nodes.</paragraph>
            <important>
                <paragraph>The example architecture used in this guide is a minimum configuration, and
                    is not intended for production system installations. It is designed to
                    provide a minimum proof-of-concept for the purpose of learning about
                    OpenStack. For information on creating architectures for specific use cases,
                    or how to determine which architecture is required, see the <reference name="Architecture Design Guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/arch-design/">Architecture
                        Design Guide</reference><target ids="architecture-design-guide" names="architecture\ design\ guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/arch-design/"></target>.</paragraph>
            </important>
            <paragraph>This example architecture differs from a minimal production architecture as
                follows:</paragraph>
            <bullet_list bullet="*">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Networking agents reside on the controller node instead of one or more
                        dedicated network nodes.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Overlay (tunnel) traffic for self-service networks traverses the management
                        network instead of a dedicated network.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
            <paragraph>For more information on production architectures, see the <reference name="Architecture Design Guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/arch-design/">Architecture Design
                    Guide</reference><target dupnames="architecture\ design\ guide" ids="id1" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/arch-design/"></target>, <reference name="OpenStack Operations Guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/ops-guide/">OpenStack Operations Guide</reference><target ids="openstack-operations-guide" names="openstack\ operations\ guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/ops-guide/"></target>, and <reference name="OpenStack Networking Guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/ocata/networking-guide/">OpenStack Networking Guide</reference><target ids="openstack-networking-guide" names="openstack\ networking\ guide" refuri="https://docs.openstack.org/ocata/networking-guide/"></target>.</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-hwreqs"></target>
            <figure ids="id2 figure-hwreqs" names="figure-hwreqs">
                <image alt="Hardware requirements" candidates="{'*': u'install/figures/hwreqs.png'}" uri="install/figures/hwreqs.png"></image>
                <caption><strong>Hardware requirements</strong></caption>
            </figure>
            <section ids="controller" names="controller">
                <title>Controller</title>
                <paragraph>The controller node runs the Identity service, Image service, management
                    portions of Compute, management portion of Networking, various Networking
                    agents, and the Dashboard. It also includes supporting services such as an SQL
                    database, message queue, and Network Time Protocol (NTP).</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Optionally, the controller node runs portions of the Block Storage, Object
                    Storage, Orchestration, and Telemetry services.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The controller node requires a minimum of two network interfaces.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="compute" names="compute">
                <title>Compute</title>
                <paragraph>The compute node runs the hypervisor portion of Compute that operates
                    instances. By default, Compute uses the kernel-based VM (KVM) hypervisor. The
                    compute node also runs a Networking service agent that connects instances to
                    virtual networks and provides firewalling services to instances via security
                    groups.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>You can deploy more than one compute node. Each node requires a minimum of two
                    network interfaces.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="block-storage" names="block\ storage">
                <title>Block Storage</title>
                <paragraph>The optional Block Storage node contains the disks that the Block Storage and
                    Shared File System services provision for instances.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>For simplicity, service traffic between compute nodes and this node uses the
                    management network. Production environments should implement a separate storage
                    network to increase performance and security.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>You can deploy more than one block storage node. Each node requires a minimum
                    of one network interface.</paragraph>
            </section>
            <section ids="object-storage" names="object\ storage">
                <title>Object Storage</title>
                <paragraph>The optional Object Storage node contain the disks that the Object Storage
                    service uses for storing accounts, containers, and objects.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>For simplicity, service traffic between compute nodes and this node uses the
                    management network. Production environments should implement a separate storage
                    network to increase performance and security.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>This service requires two nodes. Each node requires a minimum of one network
                    interface. You can deploy more than two object storage nodes.</paragraph>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section ids="networking" names="networking">
            <title>Networking</title>
            <paragraph>Choose one of the following virtual networking options.</paragraph>
            <target refid="network1"></target>
            <section ids="networking-option-1-provider-networks network1" names="networking\ option\ 1:\ provider\ networks network1">
                <title>Networking Option 1: Provider networks</title>
                <paragraph>The provider networks option deploys the OpenStack Networking service in the
                    simplest way possible with primarily layer-2 (bridging/switching) services and
                    VLAN segmentation of networks. Essentially, it bridges virtual networks to
                    physical networks and relies on physical network infrastructure for layer-3
                    (routing) services. Additionally, a DHCP&lt;Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
                    (DHCP) service provides IP address information to instances.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The OpenStack user requires more information about the underlying network
                    infrastructure to create a virtual network to exactly match the infrastructure.</paragraph>
                <warning>
                    <paragraph>This option lacks support for self-service (private) networks, layer-3
                        (routing) services, and advanced services such as Load-Balancer-as-a-Service
                        (LBaaS) and FireWall-as-a-Service (FWaaS).  Consider the self-service
                        networks option below if you desire these features.</paragraph>
                </warning>
                <target refid="figure-network1-services"></target>
                <figure ids="figure-network1-services" names="figure-network1-services">
                    <image alt="Networking Option 1: Provider networks - Service layout" candidates="{'*': u'install/figures/network1-services.png'}" uri="install/figures/network1-services.png"></image>
                </figure>
                <target refid="network2"></target>
            </section>
            <section ids="networking-option-2-self-service-networks network2" names="networking\ option\ 2:\ self-service\ networks network2">
                <title>Networking Option 2: Self-service networks</title>
                <paragraph>The self-service networks option augments the provider networks option with
                    layer-3 (routing) services that enable self-service networks using overlay
                    segmentation methods such as Virtual Extensible LAN (VXLAN). Essentially, it
                    routes virtual networks to physical networks using Network Address Translation
                    (NAT). Additionally, this option provides the foundation for advanced services
                    such as LBaaS and FWaaS.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>The OpenStack user can create virtual networks without the knowledge of
                    underlying infrastructure on the data network. This can also include VLAN
                    networks if the layer-2 plug-in is configured accordingly.</paragraph>
                <target refid="figure-network2-services"></target>
                <figure ids="figure-network2-services" names="figure-network2-services">
                    <image alt="Networking Option 2: Self-service networks - Service layout" candidates="{'*': u'install/figures/network2-services.png'}" uri="install/figures/network2-services.png"></image>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
